Sasuke's Answer
((柱間：ハァ　ハァ　ハァ。
（マダラ）ハァ　ハァ　ハァ。
This time...
今度は　お前が届かないのさ。
you're not going to
reach the other side!
I'm the one still standing.
立っているのは俺だ。
あのときとは逆だな。
Opposite from the last time.
届いたばかりの夢を→
I just want to protect...
守りたいんだ。　俺は。
the dream I finally realized.
I don't want anymore...
これ以上は…。
ずいぶんと落ち込んで見えるぞ。
柱間。
You look pretty depressed, Hashirama.
（マダラ）今度こそ
開き直りはできないか。
Can't perk back up this time, eh?
（柱間）はらわたを見せ合うことは
できねえだろうか。
Can't we show each other
our guts?
（マダラ）まずは　この考えを
捨てねえことと→
The first steps are for us to
not give up on our ideals
自分に力をつけることだろうが。
and to get a lot stronger.
ここに俺たちの集落をつくろう。
Let's build our settlement here!
つかもうとすれば→
They say where there's a will,
there's a way...
出来ないことはなかったってのに。
俺は。
And yet, I...
これから夢が現実になる。
That dream is now becoming reality.
（マダラ）木遁分身…。
A Wood Style Clone...
俺が後ろをとられるとは。
I can't believe my back was taken...
I will protect our...no, my village.
俺は俺たちの…
いや　俺の里を守る。
何があろうとも。
No matter what.
里を守ることが何より人を→
I still believe to this day
that protecting the village
will lead to the protection of
the people, shinobi, and children!
忍を　子供を守ることになると
俺は今でも信じる。
たとえそれが友であろうと
兄弟であろうと→
I will not forgive anyone
who threatens the village.
我が子であろうと
里に仇なす者は許さぬ。
Be they a friend...sibling...
or even my own child...
(変わったな。　柱間))
You've changed...Hashirama.
＜柱間：俺はこのとき
覚悟を決めた。
I made up my mind right then...
to endure in order to watch
over the present.
今を見守るために
耐え忍ぶ覚悟をだ＞
((本末転倒だな。
You've got your priorities backwards.
(それが里の闇になる…　いずれ))
Ultimately... It shall someday
lead the village to darkness.
（柱間）そうして
マダラと俺との戦いは終わった。
And thus...my battle with Madara
came to an end.
今　マダラがどう復活したのかは
わからぬが→
I don't know how Madara
returned to life now.
I definitely killed my friend...
俺は確実に友を殺した。
里のために。
For the sake of the village.
そう　里とは→
That's right...
The village...
始まりに
マダラと俺が望んだ里とは→
that Madara and I first envisioned...
一族と一族をつなげるものだった。
is something that joined
one clan to another.
無秩序から秩序を形づくり→
It was an invaluable cornerstone
that created order out of chaos,
それを保つための大切な要だった。
then maintained it.
子供たちを守り
無駄な争いを避け→
It protected the children and
averted pointless conflict.
平和を実現するものだった。
It made peace a reality.
However...it gave rise to despair,
だが　キミの兄→
イタチが背負ったような闇を
生み出してしまった。
the kind that your brother Itachi
was forced to bear.
Perhaps what Madara said
was correct, after all.
マダラの言ったことは
正しかったのかもしれん。
この状況を
見据えていたのかもしれん。
Perhaps he foresaw
this state of affairs.
この状況を作りあげてしまった
忍とは　俺だ。
I am the shinobi who created
these circumstances.
Furthermore, I am also the one
who considered them acceptable.
そして　それをよしとした忍も
俺でしかない。
忍とは　目標に向け
耐え忍ぶものだと。
I believe that shinobi are those
who endure for a purpose.
But depending on what that purpose is,
a shinobi can change.
ただ何を目標に置くのかで
忍も変わる。
Just as Madara...and I did.
マダラと俺のように。
（サスケ）忍とは　忍とは耐え忍ぶもの。
Shinobi...
Shinobi are those who endure...
in order to achieve their goals.
目標を叶えるために。
俺にとって
それが里づくりだった。
For me, it was building a village.
But it seems Madara
found something else.
だが　マダラは
別のものを見つけたようだ。
さっき大蛇丸とやらが言った→
This plan of Madara's that
Orochimaru mentioned earlier...
マダラが復活し
この世の忍を消すつもりとは→
To erase all the shinobi in this world...
I don't know what
that means in literal terms, but...
具体的にどのようなものかは
わからぬが。
It's the Infinite Tsukuyomi
無限月読　里も忍も→
where village, shinobi,
and citizen are all irrelevant.
国も民も関係ない→
ただ　すべてを幻術にはめ→
He intends to put everyone
under genjutsu
己の思いどおりに操ることだ。
and manipulate them as he sees fit.
俺の兄が　マダラの弟が→
To negate everything that
my older brother, Madara's younger brother...
そして　あんたたちが
守ろうとしてきた→
and all of you...
すべてのものを…
無にするものだ。
have tried to protect.
兄さんは→
My older brother inherited your will
without even talking to you.
あんたの意志を
直接　語ることもなく→
受け継ぐ者だったってことだ。
兄さんは…。
My older brother...
((フガク：イタチ　お前は
一族と里の中枢をつなぐ→
Itachi... You also serve as
the Uchiha Clan's pipeline
パイプ役でもあるのだ。
to the Village nerve center.
(それは　わかってるな？))
You know that, don't you?
＜兄さんは
一族の重責を担いながらも…＞
Even as he shouldered that
heavy responsibility for the clan...
((もはや容認できぬぞえ。
We cannot allow such a thing!
If they are going to start a revolution
and usurp our power,
それを革命とのたまい→
政権を奪取するつもりなら→
うちはは　木ノ葉の逆賊として→
we have no choice but to judge
the Uchiha as traitors of the Leaf!
処断せざるをえぬ。
Wait, Koharu.
コハル待て。
Don't rush to such a decision.
結論を急ぐな。
（ダンゾウ）しかし　ヒルゼン→
But Hiruzen, the Uchiha Clan
will not be dissuaded.
うちは一族は　もう止まらぬ。
ならば　混乱を避けるためにも→
We must take measures
to avoid mayhem.
一刻も早く手を打つべきだ。
（ダンゾウ）何も知らぬ
子供も含めてな。
And that includes innocent children.
イタチの前で言うことではない。
Do not say such things
before Itachi!
Besides, taking on the Uchiha
will be no easy task.
それに　うちは相手に
内戦となれば→
簡単にはいかぬぞ。
There's got be some sort of
strategy we can use!
何か策があるはずじゃ。
We have no time to waste.
事態は　一刻を争う。
やつらが事を起こす前に→
We must strike preemptively,
before they have a chance to act.
こちらから先手を打つのだ。
If we join forces with our respective
ANBU Black Ops
お前とわし
そして互いの暗部が手を組み→
背後から奇襲をかければ
すぐ終わる。
and launch a surprise attack
from behind,
it will be over in no time.
うちはは　かつての戦友。
The Uchiha are old comrades
in arms.
力ではなく
言葉で話しかけたい。
I want to settle this with
words first before force.
わしが策を考える。
I will come up with a strategy.
イタチ　少しでもいい→
Itachi...
Buy me some time,
however little it may be.
(できるかぎり
時間稼ぎをしてくれ))
He stood between the village
and the clan in their strife...
＜里と一族の対立の間に立ち＞
((フガク：そうか　お前は
向こうについたか。
I see... So you've aligned
with the other side?
（イタチ）父さん　母さん　俺は。
Father, Mother...
I...
（ミコト）わかってるわ　イタチ。
I know, Itachi.
イタチ　最後に約束しろ。
Itachi, just promise me this.
サスケのことは　頼んだぞ。
Take care of Sasuke.
わかっている。
I will.
（フガク）恐れるな
それが　お前の決めた道だろ。
Do not fear.
This is the path you have chosen.
（フガク）お前に比べれば
我らの痛みは　一瞬で終わる。
Compared to you,
our pain will be over in an instant.
考え方は違っても
お前を誇りに思う。
Even if our philosophies differ,
I am proud of you.
(（フガク）お前は　本当に優しい子だ))
You are truly a kind child.
＜両親すら手にかけ＞
He even killed his own parents...
((暁の　うちはイタチが
死んだという情報が入った。
We received intel that Itachi Uchiha
of the Akatsuki is dead.
お前らのビンゴブックにも
対象外の印を付け　外しておけ。
Put a mark on his image and
remove him from your Bingo Book.
裏切り者も　ついに死んだか。
So that traitor is dead at last.
しかし　あのイタチを　いったい
誰がやったんです？　隊長。
But Captain,
who was able to kill him?
弟の　うちはサスケだそうだ。
Looks like it was
his younger brother, Sasuke.
同胞殺しが　同胞に殺されるとは
皮肉なもんだ。
How ironic...
His own brother killed the one
who slaughtered their kin.
Serves him right!
罰ですよ　それだけの悪行を
やったんすからね。
After that atrocious thing he did!
あげく　暁にまで入って
木ノ葉を襲う始末。
Not only that, he joined up
with the Akatsuki
and came after the Leaf Village!
あいつは　木ノ葉の歴史上
稀に見る大悪人ですよ。
He's the most notorious villain
in Hidden Leaf history!
I wish we got our hands on him first!
(こいつだけは　俺たちの手で
倒したかったぜ！))
＜一族殺し　抜け忍の汚名を
浴びながらも→
He was forced to kill
his own clan and
endure the brand as
a Rogue Ninja...
Yet, he continued to keep
an eye on the organization
里に仇なす組織を　監視し続けた＞
that wanted to harm the village.
そして　死してなお。
And even in death...
I'll have protected my village
((イタチ：俺は　木ノ葉隠れの
うちはイタチとして→
as Itachi Uchiha
of the Leaf once again.
(もう一度
忍里を守ることができる))
I have no more regrets.
兄さんは
あんた以上に耐え忍んだ。
My older brother endured longer
and harder than you.
And died stating he was proud
to be Leaf Shinobi.
そして　木ノ葉の忍であることを
誇りだと語って死んだ。
あんたを　いちばん理解した忍が
うちは一族だったとは　皮肉だな。
Isn't it ironic that the shinobi who
understood you more than anyone else...
was from the Uchiha Clan?
（扉間）お前の兄だけではない。
Your brother was not the only one.
（扉間）わしの部下に
お前の兄と同じような→
I had a subordinate
named Kagami Uchiha
who was much like your brother.
うちはカガミという男がいた。
二代目　あんたは
うちは嫌いじゃなかったか？
Second Hokage... I thought
you despised the Uchiha.
（扉間）そういうことではない。
That's not entirely true.
わしは　どの一族とて→
I treated anyone who posed
a danger to the village,
里にとって　危険性があるものを
注意深く　とらえていただけだ。
no matter what clan they belonged to,
with extreme caution.
（扉間）うちはは　特に
それを考慮するべき→
And there's no doubt that
the Uchiha Clan warranted my suspicions...
一族だったのは　確かだ。
だが　本来　愛情に深い
うちはだからこそ→
The Uchiha just happened
to be a clan
particularly disposed
to be considered as such.
But, it is also because
they could feel such deep love
ときには　お前の兄や
うちはカガミのように→
that there were quite
a few Uchiha over the years
一族の枠をこえて→
like your brother and Kagami...
里のために　尽くしてくれた者も
少なからずいた。
who could transcend
the boundaries of the clan
and devote themselves to the village.
里とは　一族と一族の枠を
取り払うものだと→
My elder brother believed the village
was something that could
eliminate the framework of clans.
兄者は考えた。　まあ→
そう簡単にはいかぬのも
事実だったが。
Well, the reality is...
This wasn't so simple.
（扉間）兄者　柱間の甘さ
うちはマダラの危うさ→
The idealism of
my elder brother Hashirama...
And the danger that Madara posed...
Mediating between these two things,
この２人の間を　取り持ちつつ
里を守り　作り固めるのが→
and protecting and
strengthening the village
were my duties as
the Second Hokage.
二代目の　わしの役目だった。
うちはカガミの子孫が　うちはシスイだ。
Shisui Uchiha was
a descendant of Kagami Uchiha.
お前の兄　イタチの友だった　男じゃ。
He was a friend of
your older brother Itachi.
Many, including myself, embraced
the First Hokage's Will of Fire.
わしを含め　多くの者が
初代様の　火の意志を受け継いだ。
ただ　わしは
誰より甘い忍だったかもしれん。
But perhaps, I was more naïve
than any other shinobi.
I wasn't able to continue
the Second Hokage's task
二代目様の里づくりを
うまく引き継げなかった。
of village-building skillfully enough.
そのため　ダンゾウに
里の闇を背負わせてしまった。
Which is how I ended up burdening Danzo
with the village's darkness.
ダンゾウも　復讐として　俺がやった。
I killed Danzo in vengeance.
やつは最後　卑怯な手を
使ってでも里を守ると→
Until the end, he spoke that
he would protect the village,
no matter how dirty the means.
公言してたが…。
どうやら　わしは　火影として
失敗ばかりしてしまったようじゃ。
It seems I've failed miserably
time after time as the Hokage.
今の　このような状況を作ったのは
自分の責任でもあるのう。
I guess I'm responsible for creating
the situation that exists now.
（ミナト）いや　三代目のせいじゃない。
No... You're not to blame, Lord Third.
You did everything you could
for the sake of the village respectably.
あなたは　しっかり里のために
尽くされ　全うされた。
九尾の里　襲来のときに
俺が倒れてしまった。
I'm the one who died during
the Nine Tails' attack on the village!
あなたに　火影として
期待されていたのに→
You had such high hopes for me
as the Hokage...
その期待にそえなかった。
And I couldn't live up to them.
（大蛇丸）私を差し置いてまで
選ばれたのにね。
I'll say... After he passed over me
and picked you.
（大蛇丸）
みんな　残念がってたわよ。
Everyone was so disappointed.
大蛇丸様　少しすねてます？
Lord Orochimaru...
You sound like you're pouting.
（大蛇丸）フフッ　三代目の前だから
少しね。
A little...since the Third Hokage
is right here.
Had I lived, perhaps I could
have helped to foil
俺が生きていれば
うちはクーデターの計画も→
the Uchiha's plans for
a coup d'état much sooner...
もっと未然に防ぐ協力が
できたかもしれない。
Now then... Sasuke...
さぁ…　サスケ君→
What will you do?
どうするの？　里を潰すのか→
Will you destroy the village?
それとも…。
Or...
((許せ　サスケ
また今度にしよう。
Sorry, Sasuke...
Let's do it some other time.
許せ　サスケ　また今度だな。
Sorry, Sasuke. Let's do it next time...
俺がうとましいか？
You probably hate me, huh?
ただ　お前と俺は
唯一無二の兄弟だ。
But, we only have each other
as siblings.
お前のこえるべき壁として
俺は　お前とともにあり続けるさ。
I'm always going to
be there for you,
even if it's only as an obstacle
for you to overcome.
たとえ　憎まれようともな。
Even if you do hate me...
それが　兄貴ってもんだ。
That's what big brothers are for.
俺を疑ってるってわけか？
You all suspect me?
（イタチ）貴様など　殺す価値もない→
There is no value in killing you now...
my foolish little brother.
愚かなる弟よ
この俺を殺したくば恨め　憎め。
If you wish to kill me,
resent me, hate me,
そうして　醜く生きのびるがいい。
and survive...in obscurity.
あんたの言ったとおり
あんたを恨み　憎み　そして→
I did what you said...
I resented you and
hated you...
and I survived just so I...
あんたを殺すためだけに　俺は…。
俺は生きてきた！　うぉ～！
so I could kill you!
今　お前などに興味はない。
I have no interest
in someone like you...
なぜ弱いか　足りないからだ→
You're weak,
because you don't have enough...
憎しみが。
hate.
（イタチ）俺は　お前にいつも
許せとウソをつき→
I always lied to you and
asked you to forgive me.
この手で　お前のことを
ずっと遠ざけてきた。
Deliberately keeping you at
a distance by my own hand.
お前を巻き込みたくはなかった。
All because I didn't want you
to get caught up in any of this.
だが　今はこう思う。
お前が　父を母を→
But now, I believe...
That perhaps you could have changed
Father, Mother,
and the rest of the Uchiha.
うちはを変えることが
できたかもしれないと。
俺がはじめから
お前とちゃんと向き合い→
If I had been open with you
from the start...
同じ目線に立って
真実を語り合っていれば→
And looked you straight in the eyes
and told you the truth,
失敗した俺が　今さら
お前に上から多くを語っても→
then I wouldn't have had
to stand before you,
from above, as a failure,
telling you all of this.
伝わりはしない。
だから　今度こそ
本当のことを　ほんの少しだけ…。
So this time... I want to impart
this truth to you...
俺のことをずっと許さなくていい。
You don't ever have to forgive me.
お前がこれからどうなろうと…。
And no matter what you do
from here on out, know this...
(俺はお前をずっと愛している))
I will love you always.
俺は戦場へ行く。
この里を　イタチを無にはさせん！
I'm going to the battlefield!
I won't let the village,
and Itachi become nothing!
決まりだ。　扉間　外へ飛ぶ準備ぞ。
It's been decided then!
Tobirama!
Prepare to fly us outside!
飛雷神を使おうにも
今は縛られておる。
Even if I wanted to use Flying Raijin,
I'm bound right now.
大蛇丸とやら　お前はどうする？
Orochimaru, was it?
What will you do?
お前は　サスケに付くと
さっき言ったはずじゃがの。
You said earlier that
you'd follow Sasuke.
もちろん　同行しましょう。
Of course... We will accompany him.
（水月）え～　ジュ　重吾は？
What?!
J-Jugo, what about you?
（重吾）俺も同行する。
サスケを守るのは俺の役目だからな。
I'm going too.
It's my job to protect Sasuke.
《最強ゾンビ４体　バケモノ３人。
Four super-strong zombies...
Three monsters...
こんなのについて行ったら
確実に死ぬ。
If I tag along, I'm dead for sure!
隙をみて逃げよう》
I'm making a break for it
when I see a chance!
（柱間）ほぉ
ここからの眺めは懐かしいぞ。
This view brings back memories!
《今だよね》
It's now or never!
グエッ　なんだ？
（香燐）やっぱサスケか　てめえ！
What the hell?!
It's you after all, Sasuke!
グハッ！
チャクラ感じたんで　まさかと思って→
I sensed your chakra
and I couldn't believe it,
引き返してみりゃ～よ。
so I backtracked and look what I find!
香燐？
ほぉ　かつての良質な実験体が→
Karin...
Oh my... So many of my best experiments
gathered here in one place!
こうも集まるとはね。
てめえ　ぜってえ許さねえから！
You bastard...!
I'll never forgive you!
すまなかった　香燐。
I'm sorry, Karin.
て　てめえ　そんな言葉
許されると…　こら…。
You bastard! As if a simple apology
will get you off the hook...
ろくでなし。
you good for nothing...
相変わらずサスケ君に弱そうね　香燐。
I see you still have
a weakness for Sasuke, Karin...
あのね　大蛇丸様　サスケがね
うちをね　刺してね。
Listen, Lord Orochimaru!
Sasuke...had the gall...
to stab me and...
奇遇ね。　私もよ。
What a coincidence. Me too.
でも今は　サスケ君に協力してる。
But I'm helping Sasuke now.
ちょうどいいわ。
あなたも協力なさい。
This is perfect timing. You help too.
え～　しかたねえな。
What?!
I guess I have no choice...
誰ぞ？
チャクラとあの赤髪からして→
Who is she?
Judging from the chakra
and that red hair...
うずまき一族だな。
She's from the Uzumaki Clan.
One more idiot joins the pack.
《連中の中に
更にバカが１人加わるとは→
マダラもびっくりだろうよ》
I bet Madara will be surprised.
大蛇丸　どうしてサスケに
協力することにしたのじゃ？
Orochimaru...
Why did you decide to help Sasuke?
お前は里を潰そうとしていたのに。
You were trying to destroy the village.
カブトの中に入っていてわかった。
After being inside Kabuto,
I realized something...
私の生き方を真似し→
He imitated the way I lived and
tried to possess everything,
すべてを蓄積していたカブトも
失敗した。
and failed.
今はサスケ君の違う生き方に
興味があるだけ。
So now, I'm just curious about
the different path Sasuke has chosen.
（大蛇丸）あの子はカブトと違い
私を真似なかったから。
Unlike Kabuto, Sasuke didn't copy me.
火影たちよ　里を見守ってきた
この顔岩の上より→
Fellow Hokage!
As we stand atop the Great Stone Faces
that have watched over
the Hidden Leaf...
しっかりと里を
目に焼き付けようぞ！
Let us burn this sight of
the village into our memory!
はぁ。
やっと息子に会える。　ナルト→
I'm finally going to see my son.
Naruto, I wasn't able to do
anything for you as a father...
今まで父として
何もしてあげられなかった分→
大きなプレゼントを持っていくよ。
I'll make it up to you by
bringing you a huge present.
さて　久しぶりの戦争じゃ。
気を引き締めていかんとな。
All right! It's been a while
since my last war!
I'd be
マダラ…　今度こそ倒す！
不謹慎だが　慣れ親しんだ友に
会えるのは楽しみでもあるな。
待ってろよ　マダラ！
（柱間）いつの世も戦いよ。
だが　戦争もこれで最後ぞ。
いくぞ！
オープニングを飾るのは　この曲です！
ワン・ツー　ワン・ツー！
水前寺清子さん→